Never forget why you are the church.
And we'll make this happen.
This is the last night of this particular semester, so it
has been a huge success, a huge impact,
and I'm very glad that y'all are with us once again, okay?
let's pray.
Father we thank you, Lord, for this night.
And we thank you for just all the men that are gathered here together in
your name, thinking anything about discipleship.
And so, Lord God, I pray that you just, you teach us tonight, God.
And God, I pray that, Lord, this is not a end of anything,
but this is just the training to continue, Lord, to build relationships and help men win.
God, we thank you.
We love you, in Jesus name, pray.
anybody said?
Amen.
We're looking at the last lesson, and we've looked at a lot this year, but we're
looking at a man and the fear of man.
This is another one that, if, as
men thinking about it, it is harder to
say out loud, the fact that, man, you know, I have
some insecurities, or I have, uh, some fear of other people's
opinions, and and that, that dictates my life.
Like, we would never really say that out loud,
but our actions sometimes show it.
Right?
Our insecurities sometimes show it.
And so if you would, just if you're taking notes or
whatever, write down a few key passages, you can go home and read them.
But Psalm 145.
Psalm 91.
And Ephesians 4 are all key
passages for this.
I'm going to read you Colossians 323 before
I do, that was Psalm 145.
Psalm 91 and Ephesians 4 talking about a man in
the fear of man, but Colossians 323 says this.
It says, um, whatever you do.
Do your work heartedly as for the Lord, rather than for men.
And then if you continue there in verse 24, it says knowing
that from the Lord,
You will receive the reward of the inheritance.
It is the Lord Christ whom you serve.
So in other words, we have to understand, and we, our life
is to be lived, for the Lord and nobody else.
However, when you live your life for the Lord, here's
the caveat here that I want us to understand.
Because a lot of people take what I'm, you know, before
we even get to the lesson, a lot of people will take this and say, well, you know what?
It doesn't matter what people think, well, hold on.
understand something.
What people think about you is what they see about you.
And so we got to balance this with some good old common sense.
Right?
So if you're walking in the light as he is
in the light, then people are gonna think about you, that you have faith in the Lord.
And so don't sit here and use this as an excuse
of living in sin, living in unfaithfulness,
or living in disobedience, or living in apathy, and someone say something,
hey, man, you're not you're not where you need to be.
Oh, well, I don't serve you, so I don't care what you think.
No, no, no.
If there's a brother rebuking you of your sin, that's
a biblical mandate and responsibility we have for each other.
So I want to set the table here in the fact of, we're
talking about, we are not to fear man, but
we are to fear God, and when we fear God, we will serve each
other in the obedience of the Lord.
So we want to talk about that, okay?
But, uh, that was Colossians 3, 23.
So number one, are you seeking man's approval?
The fear of man brings a snare.
Proverbs 29, verse 25 says this.
Let me read it to you real quick.
Let me find it.
The fear of man brings a snare, but he who trusts in the Lord
will be exalted.
So what even is the fear of man?
Well, we see that the fear of man takes God's people captive
and has made many preachers, politicians,
and parents in this country prisoners.
What does that look like?
When we fear man, rather than God,
what happens is, is we make our decisions based
on what they think and what they desire.
And in doing so very often, we contradict
what God desires for us.
Uh, this morning, it was, it was, uh, it was
crazy, and, and, you know, River came up and said,
hey, by the way, daddy, um, me
and Lily promised each other that we were going to Chili's today.
That mean, so we got to go to Chile's now, because I,
because I promised her we'd go.
And I told her, I said, well, hold on.
I said, um, there, you
made a promise that you cannot fulfill.
You have no authority to hold that promise.
And the entire, the entire stinking,
uh, Sunday after church, she was like, my day is ruined.
You've ruined my day.
There's nothing you can do to help my day be better.
And so you know what I did?
I was like, okay, I'm not gonna try that.
And I said, I just let her complain and gripe, and I said, look, you got about 5 more minutes of this.
And I'm about to lose it.
That's what I told her.
I said, this is this is too much.
And then I said, and she said, can I have a poppy?
Anyone know what a poppy is, that healthy drink or whatever?
So I said, she said, can I have a poppy?
I said, no, no, your day's already ruined.
I not gonna waste a poppy on a ruined day?
Absolutely not.
She comes, she said, well, that'll make it that'll make it feel better.
And I said, But you already told me your day was ruined.
And what I'm trying to say is, is that attitude that she had,
I could have let that dictate my entire day.
I could have been sitting there saying, Listen, hey, I'm sorry, I do this, I do that.
Like, you know what?
Forget it, let's go to Chile's, let's do this.
When I knew that it was not a good...
We didn't need to go to Chili's.
Now, as silly as that is, if you put that into,
you know, career, if you put that like in the church, for example, as a
pastor, if I went on every single opinion that
all y'all had, there'd be nothing to get done.
Absolutely nothing.
If I sat there and said, what do you think about this situation?
You tell me, okay, what do you think about this situation?
And then I've started managing and
stewarding the church and the flock in a way of, well, if I do this, that person's gonna be mad.
If I do this, this person's gonna be mad.
Listen, that's the fear of man.
What that does is that paralyzes a man where they are.
Okay?
One guy said this.
I believe the day has come that we need to ask God for godly content for the approval
of men and a better appetite for the approval of God.
And until we get to that point in our lives, we will not know the
power of God in our lives.
We will be kept prisoner of what everybody else thinks,
and we will not know the joy that God intended for us as a Christian.
Charles Spursion said, if we fear God, we have nothing else to fear.
Listen, if we're fearing him and serving him, we don't have to worry about anything.
We're doing what we're supposed to be doing.
Psalm 145-19.
He will fulfill the desires of those who fear him.
And so understand that, you know, wisdom starts with the fear of the Lord.
Understanding knowledge.
We have to fear God to get that.
So we're going to look at 3 things tonight.
Speaking of the snare, right?
Remember, Proverbs 29, verse 25.
It says the fear of man brings a snare, but he who trusts in the Lord will be exalted.
So the 1st snare we see, number one, we see the snare of insecurity.
Insecurity is the result of placing my confidence and
trust in people or things that can be taken away from me.
For example, job titles, children, spouse, money,
401k, all the things that we like to put our trust in.
See, what we like to do is we like to put our trust in things that are tangible.
Things that we can, quote unquote, control.
Me and my dad was talking this weekend just about, uh,
friendships and and and relationships and all
the things that happens in a church and how it's awesome to be.
And I made a very cynical remark.
I said, well, you know, it's just a matter of time before people just, you know, leave and
then God replaced them and then someone leaves and God.
And that's just because that's what I've seen so often.
That's why I pointed out brother John Claiborne this morning.
When I saw him, it just took me back to the
beginning of all this, and it was just a really cool thing to see, and the
fact that he hadn't been here in probably 8 or 9 years, and he's
here again because we're baptizing his great granddaughter.
Like that, to me, was just a really cool moment.
But when you look at the insecurity, you start to
think, man, if I don't have this person in my life, then I just,
you know, I can't get nothing done, if I don't have, if I don't have this
much money in the bank, I can't get nothing done, we get into a snare
that we don't get anything done.
Young couples right now, they say, well, we can't get married until we have enough money in the bank.
You know what my father-in-law told me when I asked for his daughter's hand?
You'll never have enough money.
My whole conversation plan in my head with brother Randy
was, let me tell you how much I make.
Let me tell you, my plans.
Let me tell you, you know what I'm saying?
Like, let me tell you, you know, where we're gonna try to live.
Let me take my five year plan, tenure plan.
And he literally stopped me in my tracks to stop, Jacob.
He said, I don't care about all that.
You're not gonna have enough money.
You just need to love her.
And I was like, okay.
And guess what?
We haven't always had enough money, but God's always made it happen.
And so that that fear.
Job titles, right?
Children, spouses, again, all these things, we place
our confidence and trust in people or things, and
they can be taken away in a heartbeat.
If you're motivated by the praise of men, hear me now, it's
hit me like a ton of bricks.
If you're motivated by the praise of men, you will be defeated by their criticism.
People, man, listen, people can come to me and compliment me on a sermon, and
I can have 15 people come and say, man, that was awesome.
God really used you in my life today and I love that.
I love hearing that because it's like the work and
the effort and the reverence I have for God's word,
you know, it bears fruit.
But one person can say, man, I just didn't like that, and that's
what I that's what I infatuate on.
That's the fear of man.
If you're motivated by the praise of men, you'll be defeated by the criticism.
Security is placing my confidence and trust in that which cannot
be taken away from me.
And the only, the only, uh, secure thing
in our life is the Lord and the things of God.
So we see the snare of insecurity, but we also see the
snare of ignorance, right?
If doubt replaces all, you will soon give up
on all the gospel disciplines of the Christian life.
You know, we let it talk about scripture sometimes, and,
you know, we want to know everything, and we want to understand everything, and we want to do this.
We want to do that.
And it's fun conversations, but sometimes we're it's
almost like we're trying to explain the awe out of God.
I don't know everything about God, but I know he's awesome.
And the fact that I don't know everything about him causes
awe in my life towards him.
There's almost, it's not necessarily a mystery, but
there's just this, this, this aspect of you are so much
greater than me, yet you love me.
God, you are awesome.
Right?
But we get in a snare of ignorance, do we think that, well, if I don't know everything, then
what's the point?
If I don't know what is happening, then why do I even care?
It's kind of like those people that say, you know what, I'll just try to make it to the rapture
and I'll get my life to Christ during a tribulation.
Listen, I wouldn't bet on that.
Right?
Listen, what we know about God is this, that he still loved the world that
he gave us only begotten son.
And whosoever believes in him should not perish, but have every life.
We know that Jesus said, if you let me keep my commandments.
We know that he said he's the way, the truth, and life, no man comes to the Father except through him.
We know these things.
Let's live in what we know.
and walk in that obedience.
See, ignorance causes lawlessness, which refers
to the state of living apart from the law or will of God.
People say, well, I just didn't know.
Yes, you did.
You know that the law is written on our hearts, right?
Do you know that?
You know, God knew what he was doing when he created everything.
In other words, so often we say, well, I didn't, I didn't, I got pulled over one time.
Anyone got pulled over?
Easy, Mike, how many times, brother?
Mike's like, yes.
That's what I do, preacher.
Well, we're taking him off the insurance.
anyway.
But listen, so I'm gonna tell you, I'm gonna tell you something, and
you can use it against me if you want, okay?
Y'all love doing that, but I'm going to tell you anyway, I'm not going to stop preaching like God puts on my heart.
But I got pulled over going to Joel's house of all places.
And we were having a little meeting and it was right by us.
I was literally almost there.
And I was going, I think, 43 or something
down, uh, uh, Blair, Blair Lane.
Does anyone know what I'm talking about?
Blair Lane.
Anyone know what I'm talking about?
Okay.
You know, them, them, them cops be sitting there, you
know, they don't got anything else to do.
So I just sit right there.
Just kidding, buddy.
You got so much to do.
I'm sorry.
Anyway, so.
But listen, so, so you, you ever pass
a cop, instantly look back and you're like, please don't turn the lights on.
Please don't turn the lights on.
Please don't pull out.
I do it every time, whether I'm speeding or not, right?
It's just something I have a guilty conscience, man.
And so I passed this cop and dude, whoop.
There's a lot.
So I'm like, that ain't for me.
And then, like, they're following, like, oh my, that's for me.
And so I'm going, they can, they can see me from their house.
I'm like, this is the most embarrassing thing ever.
I'm getting pulled over outside of a member's home.
And he said, uh, you know, I roll the window down.
I instantly start crying.
No, I'm just kidding.
don't cry.
But I did, I did, you know, 10 and two.
I'm sitting there like, listen, I ain't messing around like some people do.
Like, yes, sir, no, sir.
What would you like?
Like, you know, I'm not in the browse, but what you need.
you know what I'm saying?
Like whatever.
And then we're sitting there and he goes, hey, sir, do you know what the speed limit is?
And I said, uh, yes, sir.
It's 40, isn't it?
And he goes, no, sir, it's 30.
I said, oh, I'm so sorry, officer.
I thought it was 40.
I thought I was just going 3 over.
Now listen to him now.
I straight, bold face lied to him.
I did.
I wanted him to think that I did not realize I was speeding as much as I was.
But I got caught in sin.
Does that make sense?
I can sit here and say, well, Officer, I was ignorant.
But then on you, then in that moment I had a decision to make, and I didn't make the right decision.
Understand that ignorance is not bliss.
And and and living a life and and thinking,
well, it's okay because I don't know.
I don't know any better.
No, no, no, no.
If you're a believer, the Holy Spirit guides you in truth.
Reminds you of what you've been taught.
In other words, we are guided in such a way that we know what is
right and what is wrong and we don't have to be told.
You hear me?
Y'all judge me pretty hardcore right now, aren't you?
That's okay.
Yeah, you are?
That's all right.
Uh, he gave me a warning.
anyway, so...
But listen, I was convicted.
And so not of like a crime of spiritual things.
But again, it is as though God had no law or not had ever given his law to men.
It's one of the most grievous consequences of ignorance of
God is living apart from his law.
And so I believe that we here in this room, we understand God's law.
We know God's word.
And if we don't, we're seeking God's word.
So we cannot stay in the snare of ignorance.
The more we reject the knowledge of God, the more unrestrained
and immoral we become.
Those who have no knowledge of God or his will run unrestrained
in sin and act as self-appointed leaders apart from God.
You can look at judges 176 and 2125 for that.
So we see the snare of ignorance, but also, number three,
we see the snare of idolatry.
Idolatry is putting what others think of me ahead of what God thinks of me.
Idolatry occurs whenever we worship anything or anyone other
than the living God.
And guys, when we when we look at the term worship, we think
that it's just simply standing in a group of people with
our hands raised possibly.
And, you know, if your Carlos through up here, if you're me, they're right here, you know what I'm saying?
We kind of had, we kind of switch out, you know, on Sunday morning.
But we think that's worship.
Guys, can I tell you something, worship is devotion.
In other words, if you're devoted to God, day by day,
you are worshiping him with your life.
But if you're devoted to anything else or anyone else, you in
turn are worshiping someone other than God.
And so we have to understand that we look at this, this,
uh, term of idolatry is almost this like ancient term of like
having the little the little wooden figurines in the tent.
Let me just tell you something.
Our lives are full of idolatry or temptations
to be idolaters.
And so we have to be careful.
If you stop depending on God, you won't know when he's gone.
What that means is this.
Sin will, and you've heard this, but sin keeps you longer
than you ever want to stay.
Right?
It takes you further than you ever plan to go.
And before you know it, if you continue to stop depending
on God and you continue in your sin, you're going to look around one day and say, how did I get here?
Understand King Saul, he started anointed.
He did not finish anointed.
I want to start and finish well.
Amen.
And by the way, it doesn't matter how you started.
We're here today.
And God has grace for that.
We are our own barrier to experiencing
fullness and freedom in Christ.
So we have uh, 3 snares.
We got the snare of insecurity, the snare of ignorance, the snare of idolatry.
So what you see, can man's approval or God's approval?
But whoever trusts in the Lord shall be safe, looking at Proverbs 2925.
The fear of man brings a snare, but he who trusts in the Lord, will be exalted.
Galatians 110, Psalm 910.
I'm going to turn there real quick.
Galatians.
110.
I read it to you real quick.
We're going to look at 3 more things and we'll be done and get to our get to our table times.
If you want me, say amen.
Amen.
Galatians 110.
It says, for I, for am I now speaking the favor of manner of God?
Where am I striving to please men?
If I was still trying to please men, I would not be a bond servant of Christ.
In other words, scripture tells it very simply.
If you're trying to please men, then you're not being a servant or God.
So 3 things, we want to live as a man unleashed.
Right?
We don't want to, we don't want to be held back by, uh,
the fear of man, unresolved hurt, anger, the
need of approval to shape our decisions.
Guys, you know what should shape our decisions.
That's our knowledge of God and his word.
So we want to be unleashed.
don't want anything, we don't want anything holding us back.
That goes right along with a 2nd one.
Lives a man unhindered.
Right?
Hebrews 12 causes to lay aside both sin and every weight that slows us down.
That's habits, that's commitments, that's relationships, that's pursuits,
that's entertainments, financial pressures, or misplaced
responsibility that's draining our spiritual strength.
Guys, a lot of you may or know, may not know.
I know a lot of you do, but about fiber, I don't know,
I don't know how long ago it is now, but 5 or 6 years ago, it was actually how me and Billy Anderson met.
I started coaching.
And I love coaching, right?
The 1st year that we coached, Billy was the head coach.
Billy was the head coach.
We went 011.
I was like, man, Billy can't coach.
I'm just kidding.
But we had a tough team.
It was it was a pretty tough.
But we came back, we went 9 and five.
It was a better situation.
But seriously, like we, you know, but man, it was 3rd
to 5th graders, but me and Billy don't know any different.
And later on, it was me and Wesley.
We poured our heart and souls into this team.
I mean, we're like, we're running 3rd graders and 4th graders and 5th graders.
like, we're like a, you know, high school team.
You know what I'm saying?
We're trying to win.
It ain't about developments.
about winning.
And so, so, what came down to it is.
I started I started becoming hindered with my family.
In other words, I would, they would be in bed by the time I got home.
I'd always stay after practice, a long time talking.
Our Saturday mornings and really Saturdays was always just completely crushed with the games.
And so what I have to do after about 5 years, I say, I have to step back.
I have to prioritize.
This is hindering me too much.
And you know what's beautiful about it?
When you stomp something that got us put on your heart to stop,
You typically don't look back.
You just typically keep on moving forward.
So we want to live as a man unhindered.
Live as a man unashamed.
Are you living for Christ approval or trying to earn people's approval?
Listen, if your family was against Christ, where would you stand?
You don't have to answer that out loud.
I'm telling you right now, there are men in our church.
that are not here or not apart or not faithful.
Because their wife and their kids are not.
Well, why do you think they're not?
Because the leader's not.
Guys, we had to lead and protect.
And sometimes that decision is a hard one, but it's, it's pretty simple.
When we live our lives as, yes, man, we find ourselves in no man's land
with God and those, we are called delayed.
For example, I've told this before and it breaks my heart, but my 2nd,
you actually, if you were here on Wednesday, you heard Ridley.
I said, hey, we're going to pray.
She's like, no.
I was like, are you serious right now?
But I'll sit there and I'll pray, and we'll go to bedtime, and I'll
say, hey, hey, Ridley, we're going, what would you like to pray about nothing?
Well, what you mean?
You got everything going on?
Yeah.
I was like, well, let's pray.
I don't want to.
Well, guess what?
You don't have an option.
We gonna pray to God.
Why?
Because I'm the leader.
And here's the thing.
We're gonna pray because that's what God said we need to.
We need to talk with the Lord.
And I try to talk to her in that way of telling her, listen, this is not an option.
God loves us.
God cares about us.
And then guess what happens?
You know what happens?
As time goes by, she starts giving me prayer requests.
She starts praying with me.
But if I would if I would have looked for just the approval, man.
Again, I know it's a simple, silly illustration, but I would say, you know what?
That's okay.
I don't want you to go to bed mad at me or irritate her or, you know, cranky.
So we'll just skip prayer tonight.
Absolutely not.
We got to walk in the way of the Lord.
So are you seeking man's approval or are you seeking God's approval?
Amen?
All right, guys, I want to pray.
We get into our table time.
Father, we thank you, Lord.
God, I pray that we always seek your approval.
Well, God, I pray that we do so together.
God, I pray this is not something that, that, um, we
take as an excuse to isolate or an excuse to, to not
be a part or an excuse to, to unprioritize,
uh, church life and and just our devotion to each other.
God, I pray that we are devoted to discipling and being discipled.
So God, we thank you.
We love you.
In Jesus name, pray.
Everybody said.